<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>About_jenas on Apache Jena</title>
    <link>https://jena.apache.org/about_jena.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in About_jenas on Apache Jena</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language><atom:link href="https://jena.apache.org/about_jena/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Apache Jena project team members</title>
      <link>https://jena.apache.org/about_jena/team.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jena.apache.org/about_jena/team.html</guid>
      <description>In first name alphabetical order:
Aaron Coburn (acoburn) C Adam Soroka (ajs6f) CP Andy Seaborne (andy) CP VP Bruno Kinoshita (kinow) CP Chris Dollin (chrisdollin) CP Chris Tomlinson (codeferret) CP Claude Warren (claude) CP Damian Steer (damian) CP Dave Reynolds (der) CP Ian Dickinson (ijd) CP Lorenz Buehmann (lbuehmann) C Osma Suominen (osma) CP Paolo Castagna (castagna) CP Rob Vesse (rvesse) CP Stephen Allen (sallen) CP Ying Jiang (jpz6311whu) C Emeritus and Mentors:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Citing Jena</title>
      <link>https://jena.apache.org/about_jena/citing.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jena.apache.org/about_jena/citing.html</guid>
      <description>The name of the project is “Apache Jena”. That should appear as the first use in a paper and in a reference. After that &amp;ldquo;Jena&amp;rdquo; can be used. It is also a trademark of the Apache Software Foundation. This is also the industry practice.
The reference should indicate the website https://jena.apache.org/ (https is preferable). If relevant to reproducibility, or discussing performance, the release version number MUST also be included. The date of access would also be helpful to the reader.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jena architecture overview</title>
      <link>https://jena.apache.org/about_jena/architecture.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jena.apache.org/about_jena/architecture.html</guid>
      <description>There&amp;rsquo;s quite a lot of code inside Jena, and it can be daunting for new Jena users to find their way around. On this page we&amp;rsquo;ll summarise the key features and interfaces in Jena, as a general overview and guide to the more detailed documentation.
At its core, Jena stores information as RDF triples in directed graphs, and allows your code to add, remove, manipulate, store and publish that information. We tend to think of Jena as a number of major subsystems with clearly defined interfaces between them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jena Roadmap</title>
      <link>https://jena.apache.org/about_jena/roadmap.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jena.apache.org/about_jena/roadmap.html</guid>
      <description>You can view a list of the open issues on Github.
Pull requests, patches and other contributions welcome!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jena Security Advisories</title>
      <link>https://jena.apache.org/about_jena/security-advisories.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jena.apache.org/about_jena/security-advisories.html</guid>
      <description>The Jena project has issued a number of security advisories during the lifetime of the project. On this page you&amp;rsquo;ll find details of our security issue process, as a listing of our past CVEs and relevant Dependency CVEs.
Process Jena follows the standard ASF Security for Committers policy for reporting and addressing security issues.
If you think you have identified a Security issue in our project please refer to that policy for how to report it, and the process that the Jena Project Management Committee (PMC) will follow in addressing the issue.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jena-related projects and tools</title>
      <link>https://jena.apache.org/about_jena/contributions.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jena.apache.org/about_jena/contributions.html</guid>
      <description>This page lists various projects and tools related to Jena - classes, packages, libraries, applications, or ontologies that enhance Jena or are built on top of it. These projects are not part of the Jena project itself, but may be useful to Jena users.
This list is provided for information purposes only, and is not meant as an endorsement of the mentioned projects by the Jena team.
If you wish your contribution to appear on this page, please raise a GitHub issue with the details to be published.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to Apache Jena</title>
      <link>https://jena.apache.org/about_jena/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jena.apache.org/about_jena/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the Apache Jena project! Jena is a Java framework for building Semantic Web applications. Jena provides a collection of tools and Java libraries to help you to develop semantic web and linked-data apps, tools and servers.
The Jena Framework includes:
an API for reading, processing and writing RDF data in XML, N-triples and Turtle formats; an ontology API for handling OWL and RDFS ontologies; a rule-based inference engine for reasoning with RDF and OWL data sources; stores to allow large numbers of RDF triples to be efficiently stored on disk; a query engine compliant with the latest SPARQL specification servers to allow RDF data to be published to other applications using a variety of protocols, including SPARQL In April 2012, Jena graduated from the Apache incubator process and was approved as a top-level Apache project.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is Jena?</title>
      <link>https://jena.apache.org/about_jena/about.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jena.apache.org/about_jena/about.html</guid>
      <description>Jena is a Java framework for building Semantic Web applications. It provides a extensive Java libraries for helping developers develop code that handles RDF, RDFS, RDFa, OWL and SPARQL in line with published W3C recommendations. Jena includes a rule-based inference engine to perform reasoning based on OWL and RDFS ontologies, and a variety of storage strategies to store RDF triples in memory or on disk.
History Jena was originally developed by researchers in HP Labs, starting in Bristol, UK, in 2000.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
